{
  "reference_number": "9791",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The draft Productivity Commission report indicates that long term the earlier we achieve net zero emissions the better, but given NZ's\n current reliance on the dairy industry it makes sense to give a few years leeway for short-lived gases. At the same time, NZ Govt must\n\n heavily incentivise the development of technologies to enable short-lived gases to be reduced (with a view to either developing a\n replacement industry for NZ to excel in or allowing the dairy industry to become carbon efficient)."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "A functional itnl emissions trading scheme makes sense for the same reason the globalised economy makes sense - it allows\n\n industries to be centred in parts of the world that can undertake them efficiently. For example, NZ is an efficient grass-fed dairy\n producer. It doesn't make sense to shift dairy production overseas to countries that do it less efficiently (e.g. in South America or\n\n Europe). Therefore it makes sense to incentivise the production of dairy in NZ. Would be helpful if NZ could buy carbon credits off\n other countries that dont need them (e.g. countries that are more tertiary industry heavy) and continue producing dairy as efficiently\n as possible (if not carbon neutrally)."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It's too tempting. Subsequent govts may well believe that their situation is unique (e.g. if there's another global economic crisis or\n\n whatever) but in reality climate change is the biggest economic and social threat to NZ longterm and we can't keep borrowing\n time/resources off our future selves."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Delete the fuel poverty reference as it is not sufficiently applicable in NZ to warrant specific mention. In the UK their electricity is\n\ngenerated predominantly by non-renewables so the price of electricity is linked to the availability of coal etc. In NZ any electric heating\ndevices are powered by approx. 75% renewables (as we have so much hydropower)."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1) Be realistic 2) Someone needs to be accountable for a failure to comply with the plan"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Don't want the NZ ETS approach too heavily influenced by vote-grabbing."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "But not opposed to separate legislation covering that issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Regulation is great but arguably there has been under-consideration of the power of the market to get NZ firms to embrace carbon-\nefficiency. The govt is a big procurer of goods and services and has lots of market power but there doesnt seem to be any all-of-\n\ngovernment strategy to incentivising carbon efficiency. I work in the construction industry and I'm thinking specifically of how the UK\ngovt made it a requirement of contractors to have certain Building Information Modelling level capabilities before said contractor was\neligible for govt projects - this resulting in much higher BIM uptake in the UK construction industry than elsewhere. It may be possible\n\nto use the same technique to encourage low-carbon technology uptake in NZ both in the construction and other industries. It needs\nto be worth private enterprises' while to invest in carbon-lowering technologies - one way to do this is to create a market for it. That\n\nwill lower the cost of those technologies and eventually private procurers will also be able to afford the benefits."
    }
  ]
}
